GitHub actions why are they in
CP so you know when I saw that GitHub
actions ran on Windows and Linux and Mac
first of all I'm like why would you have
the GitHub Runner actions Runner work on
Windows or Mac that that seems really
weird and cool at the same time so I
went ahead and I asked chat gbt 4.0 and
here's the answer get up action Runners
are C for several reasons CP is
statically typed yeah we know CP is
crossplatform okay we know that
Microsoft now listen this is a good one
Microsoft the company that owns GitHub
also created C this means that they have
a lot of experience in blah so they had
resources for it C is also good support
uh for runners because it can run on
lots of things.net the normal reasons
you can read the rest of them pause the
video but here's the interesting thing
so I was like now wait a second didn't C
I mean sorry didn't GitHub actions exist
before Microsoft acquired GitHub and
saved GitHub if you don't know about
that we should do a whole video about
how Microsoft saved GitHub from
Financial ruin they actually did they
were about to go under and GitHub would
have disappeared from the planet if it
hadn't been for Microsoft swooping in or
some other company that has actual money
you can hate Microsoft i1 but the fact
is they had money and they kept GitHub
alive and something else happened so I
went ahead and I asked another question
from you know chat GPT here did GitHub
actions exist before did GitHub company
acquired Microsoft and the answer is no
GitHub actions did not exist before
Microsoft's
acquisition um of of this Microsoft uh
acquired GitHub in June 2018 GitHub
actions was used to automate software
workflows that were introduced in
November 2019 so the conclusion is
GitHub actions came from
Microsoft and I'm going to put that in
the column that says of likes things
about Microsoft there's plenty of things
in the column of don't like things about
Microsoft but in the column of things I
like about Microsoft one of them is
saved GitHub from Financial ruin the
second one is GitHub actions and before
you go off on well don't you hate C no I
absolutely don't I actually as as an
object-oriented programming languages go
I think C is way better than Java
of course I haven't written a single
line of java officially since
2020 uh no that's not true 2000 so yeah
I haven't done any job of officially um
so you know don't ask me about languages
especially objectoriented programming
languages I will not program in one uh
period I just won't I'm I'm too close to
retirement I don't have to do that and I
never will um so the fact that GitHub
actions and the GitHub actions Runner is
written in C is extremely intriguing
inging to me and and I I like this deep
dive I'm doing you'll have to join us um
on my twitch Channel if you want to do
some of these deep Dives with me but but
the the conclusion to this deep dive is
that the runners are actually you can
run you could run a get up runner on
Windows NT uh uh I thought for sure it
was going to be a containerized I mean
they are containers right so now my next
question is like well how is it that you
know if you have if you write your own
you know custom actions they have to be
containers those containers have to run
well they're running on a runner that's
running on Windows how does that work
well I imagine it's because there's a
container engine running on Windows NT
and windows con and and but containers
are a Linux technology which means they
got to have a VM built in there
somewhere I'm I I got questions so we'll
we'll do those questions later but the
conclusion is Runners are a Microsoft
thing they are written in C and they're
awesome